Huston-Tillotson University records, Inclusive: 1930-1935, Bulk: 1934-1935
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Huston-Tillotson University records
Inclusive: 1930-1935, Bulk: 1934-1935
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3828
Tillotson College, 1877 - 1952
3 document boxes.
The Huston-Tillotson University records consist of correspondence and financial documents from Tillotson College as University President Mary Elizabeth Branch tried to keep the college open during the Great Depression.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
Huston-Tillotson University, a small liberal arts and sciences school in Austin, Texas, has offered a quality education to scholars for many years. The school is operated today jointly by the United Church of Christ and the United Methodist Church. Historically, most of the students have been African-American, and the coeducational university has drawn a lot of support from African-American communities in Austin.
Huston-Tillotson University was originally two separate colleges, Samuel Huston College and Tillotson College, which merged in 1952 to form the current school. Both schools were religiously affiliated, Samuel Huston College with the Methodist Episcopal Church, and Tillotson College with the American Missionary Society of Congregational Churches. The materials in this collection are linked to Tillotson College in the 1930s, before the merger with Samuel Huston College to form Huston-Tillotson University in 1952.
During the 1930s, Mary Elizabeth Branch was president of Tillotson College, an all-girls junior college in Austin, Texas. Branch had received her bachelor's and master's degrees from the University of Chicago, and had served as dean of women at what was in 1928 the largest high school in the country for black girls. She came to Tillotson in 1930.
Tillotson College, like many schools, struggled to operate as usual during the Great Depression. Before Mary Branch arrived, Tillotson College was dealing with poor administration and declining student population. After her arrival, major changes began at Tillotson. She raised enough money to double the number of faculty, offer more scholarships, construct new dormitories and gymnasiums, and build better relations with the community and other schools in the area. Most of this was done during the Great Depression, when many schools were trying just to stay open. Much of the collection reflects Branch's struggles to collect tuition from students and their parents, and Tillotson College's purchases during the early 1930s.
Mary Branch's improvements were recognized on a national level when Tillotson College achieved an "A" rating from the Southern Association of Colleges in 1943, seven years after it was admitted to membership in the American Association of Colleges. Mary Branch passed away in 1944 July 9 at the height of her career. Her work to improve Tillotson College paid off when Tillotson merged with Samuel Huston College in 1952 to form the present-day Huston-Tillotson University. Huston-Tillotson continues the legacy of quality education in Austin today, originally established by Tillotson College and Samuel Huston College in the 1800s.
Scope and Content
The Huston-Tillotson University records begin in 1934 and ends in 1936. Records include letters and financial documents. Correspondence is by far the largest series, with many letters asking students and their parents to pay their tuition bills, and letters noting payments for various education-related expenses.
Arrangement
This collection was not organized prior to this finding aid. The collection arrived at The Texas Collection in two large pink box-like binders, with the materials stuffed inside.
Currently, the Huston-Tillotson University records are arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3828. Acquired 2012-10-05
Related Resources
Related references
Brown, Olive D. and Michael R. Heintze. "Branch, Mary Elizabeth." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 14.
"Huston-Tillotson College." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 14.
“Huston-Tillotson College.” Vertical File, n.d. Texas Collection, Baylor University, Waco, Texas.
Shackles, Chrystine I. Reminiscences of Huston Tillotson College. Austin, Texas: Best Printing Company, 1973.
"Tillotson College." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 14.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Tillotson College, Austin, Texas.
Subjects
African American universities and colleges -- Texas -- Austin.; African Americans -- Education (Higher).; African Americans -- Texas-- History
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Correspondence, 1930-1935; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains various letters written to and from Tillotson College. Most had something to do with the school's finances; many are from parents asking about their student, or from the college to the parents asking for the student's bill to be paid. Other letters are to various companies that the college bought supplies from, including bookcases from Gaylord, books from Barnes and Noble, and food from various area merchants. One letter orders basketball jerseys and basketballs for the college girls' team. This series is in good condition.
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 January- September 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 September 26-29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1934 October1-2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1934 October 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 3-12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 15-23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1934 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1934 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 26-31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1934 November 6-14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1934 November 6-14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 15-19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 21-27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 December 6-11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1934 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1934 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 December 19-31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 January 3-8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 January 12-19 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 January 21-26 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 February 1-9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 February 12-16 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 February 12-16 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 February 18-21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 February 18-21 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 February 25-28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 February 25-28 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 3), 1935 March 1-5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 3), 1935 March 1-5 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (3 of 3), 1935 March 4-5 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 March 8-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 March 8-13 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 14-16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 18-26 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 27-30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 1-3 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 April 6-10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 April 6-10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 10-16 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 18-30 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 May 4-14 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 May 4-14 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 May 15-20 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 May 21-28 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (1 of 2), 1935 June 11-17 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University: (2 of 2), 1935 June 11-17 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 June 20-26 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - From Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 September (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 1-11 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 12-22 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 23-24 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 October 24-31 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 3-16 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 17-22 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 November 26-30 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 December 2-10 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 December 12-19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1934 December 21-31 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 January 4-17 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 January 18- February 11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 February 13-27 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 1-12 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 13-20 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 March 21-30 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 April 12-29 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 May 1-18 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 May 29-June (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - To Huston-Tillotson University, 1935 September (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Financial Documents, 1933-1935; 2
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  This series contains various bills, receipts, and student bills generated by Tillotson College. This series is in average condition.
  - General, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Student Bills, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 20)